A Guide to the Irvine-Saunders Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
The Day Books include a day book from Maple Creek Mills dating from 1842. There is a 1867 day book with one page filled, made of a cut agricultural crop ledger. There is also in the book a pasted in notice from the Adjuctant Inspector's Office in Richmond, July 29, 1863. Dating January 18, 1872 is a subscription book for the Lee Monumental Association. Also present is a $1 donation from Alex Berkeley of Yellow Branch, Virginia. There are also farm journals dating 1855 through 1860.
A card game, 1846, called "The Game of Kings made Easy" which is based on the kings of England who reigned down to its date, is also present. The card for Henry V is missing. Many of the cards contain information of the kings of an antiquarian nature.
The Memorandum books, 1873-1874 and 1881-1894, owned by Fleming Saunders, includes employees, supplies, and construction information in the first volume. The latter has a note at its end which mentions survey data.
The Otter River Township Record Book dates from 1870-1874. There are references to road building. An entry for June 16, 1871 notes the ordering of "tickets" for road tax and township levy. Also included are lists of expenses for board members with lists of expenses for materials bought. One entry notes that B. H. Anthony, overseer of the poor, sends three paupers--one white woman and two black woman--to the poor house. Expenses for the poor house are noted. At 1874 and 1875 meetings, Fleming Saunders is mentioned as road overseer in certain districts.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of the Davis Family, Saunders Family, and related families., 1800-1904, n.d.; (3 folders). (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Cary H. Gwathmey., 1874-1894 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Eva (Smith) Saunders., 1868-1894, n.d.; (2 folders). (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Fleming and Mary (Gwathmey) Saunders., 1858-1910, n.d.; (5 folders). (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of William Watts., 1754-1794; (4 folders). (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence of William Watts., 1795-1806, n.d.; (2 folders). (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William Watts with E[ ] Meade., 1783-1789 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William Watts with Edward Randolph., 1796-1797 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William Watts with Thomas F. Scott., 1792-1798 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William Watts with John Tabb., 1784-1792 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence of William Watts with John Watts., 1784-1800 (Box Box 2)
  - Letterbook of Frank Prufer., 1873-1880 (Box Box 2)
- Business Papers
  - Accounts., 1751-1899, n.d.; (4 folders). (Box Box 2)
  - Accounts of Fleming Saunders., 1862-1904; (2 folders). (Box Box 3)
  - Accounts of William Watts., 1752-1797; (5 folders). (Box Box 3)
  - Promissory Notes and Receipts., 1754-1797; (3 folders). (Box Box 3)
  - Promissory Notes and Receipts., 1800-1905, n.d.; (4 folders). (Box Box 4)
- Legal Papers
  - Bills of Complaint., 1767-1796, n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Bonds., 1752-1787 (Box Box 4)
  - Court Dockets for Amelia County, Virginia and Lunenburg County, Virginia., 1771-1782 (Box Box 4)
  - Court Memoranda kept by William Watts., 1768-1786, n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Indentures., 1749-1788, n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Legal Day Books kept by William Watts., 1772-1773 (Box Box 4)
  - Legal Papers., 1765-1903, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Amelia County, Virginia., 1768-1789, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Amherst County, Virginia., 1795-1845, 1912, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Buckingham County, Virginia., 1767-1773 (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Campbell County, Virginia., 1787-1903 (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Cumberland County, Virginia., 1768-1785 (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Prince Edward County, Virginia., 1766-1789 (Box Box 5)
  - Legal Papers of Virginia Counties., 1755-1796 (Box Box 5)
  - Surveys., 1774-1877, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Wills., 1745-1765 (Box Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Advertisements., 1874-1905, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Church Related Papers., 1882-1904 (Box Box 5)
  - Civil War Papers., 1861-1864 (Box Box 5)
  - Educational Papers., 1848-1903, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Fragments., n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Lectures, Essays, and Poems., 1794-1843, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous., 1887-1892, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Obituaries of Fleming Saunders, Sr., Alice W. Saunders, and Peter Saunders., 1858, 1867, 1904 (Box Box 5)
  - Photographs., n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - United States Stamps: Internal Revenue Service., 1898 (Box Box 5)
- Bound Volumes
  - Blacksmith Journals kept by Fleming Saunders., 1868-1872 (Box Box 6)
  - Day Books: Miscellaneous., 1867, 1872 (Box Box 6)
  - Farm Journals., 1855-1861 (Box Box 6)
  - The Game of Kings Made Easy., 1846 (Box Box 6)
  - Maple Creek Mills Day Book., 1842 (Box Box 6)
  - Memorandum Book kept by William Watts., 1773 (Box Box 6)
  - Memorandum Books kept by Fleming Saunders., 1873-1874, 1881-1894 (Box Box 6)
  - Otter River Township Record., 1870-1875 (Box Box 6)
- Photostats of Unrelated Material
  - American Loyalist Transcripts from the New York Public Library., 1784-1786 (Box Box 7)
  - Letters of William Cowper., 1800-1812 (Box Box 7)
  - Slaughter Diary., 1807-1808 (Box Box 7)
  - Blacksmith's Account Book, Rappahannock County, Virginia., 1827-1834 (Box Box 7)
  - The Broadway Journal., 1845 (Box Box 7)
  - Eugene M. Cox: Diary, Soldiers' Almanac with memorandum., 1855, 1864 (Box Box 7)
  - Letters of John B. Webb., 1861-1862 (Box Box 7)
  - Printed re University of Virginia Volunteers(1861-1862) and the Semi-Centennial., 1880, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Last Wills and Testaments. (Box Box 7)